[Music]
so Daniel thank you for joining me I
know you've been hugely busy over the
last few days you're probably a familiar
face to many people on the channel and
maybe people aren't aware that you've
been deeply involved with the response
to this pandemic from the medical side
from the economic side liaison with
institutions and agencies and we we're
going to cover here like the situational
assessments where are we at right now
and what is the really crucial
information that people need to know and
act on right now yeah
thank you David so we are recording on
March 21st I'm saying that because we're
going to be giving a real-time
assessment and also recommendations and
many of these recommendations will have
already happened and will be on to new
things and the assessment will have
changed a few days from now so much of
this information is rapidly changing
also as a preface not a medical doctor
so I'm not giving medical advice here I
am working with a number of groups
seeking to get good information and good
response across us so as a source of
preface we'll start with a kind of
situation assessment and then what a
risk assessment of how the situation
could have full unfold based on unknowns
and different response types would be
and then response recommendations and
then some brief notes on the background
situation that has brought us here and
what the kind of bigger picture
responses need to be for systemic
fragility and catastrophic risk writ
large I'll start with just a quick note
on the nature of bias and assessing
things like this because most everyone
has seen a range of responses from this
is no big deal it's just a flu
- this is the end of the world as we
know it and so obviously most of those
responses are not particularly clearly
informed but even amongst the clearly
informed things the curves can be very
different based on how we respond and
there's a lot of unknown still we don't
know if getting the infection and
recovering will confer immunity - where
you don't get it again or if you don't
get it for across what range of changes
in mutation so given that there's also a
lot of unknowns including confounding
variables that could occur you do get a
pretty wide range of estimates so I'm
gonna speak to in the risk assessment
some of the things that could go pretty
badly if we don't respond well not
because that is definitely how it's
going to go but because it could go that
way if we don't respond preventatively
now this is a tricky thing anytime
someone is in the position of trying to
do an anticipatory response is that it
is the job in doing anticipatory risk
mitigation to assess the scenarios we
don't want to have happen to propose
remedies to prevent them from happening
then people who have status quo bias
afterwards will say see it was overblown
hype those things didn't happen but they
only didn't happen because we made the
responses so the the scenarios I'm gonna
suggest hopefully don't happen but they
could and in order to not happen they
need us to take them seriously and
respond in a way that prevents them and
then after the fact we'll say see look
they didn't happen because we responded
well so this is a really key aspect of
bias that's important now we have a
situation where we have to act without
complete knowledge the time that it
takes to get complete knowledge the
underlying situation is changing so
inaction is also a kind of action right
there is a consequence to action and
inaction and the action is not
inconsequential no matter what
doing nationwide quarantines has an a
massive effect on people's mental health
on the underlying economy on lots of
things and not doing it has a massive
effect and so we're not taking any of
that trivially trivially what we're
gonna do is given what the unknowns are
and what the knowns are what are the
various scenarios factoring the second
and third and fourth order effects how
bad do they get and what are the
responsible approaches to take that
maintain optionality for us to continue
to make better responses as we get
better information and as we get better
capabilities that's it for the preface
so diving into situational assessment I
think many people have a clearer sense
of the real risk here than they had even
a couple days ago because the awareness
of the actual risk portended is getting
clearer in terms of obviously the US
government and the UK government
starting to change their position the
paper that came out from the Imperial
College affected the positions of both
of those countries from let's just kind
of let everybody get it herd immunity
type approaches to oath that actually
it's gonna be catastrophic and won't
work and we have to be serious about
social distancing and quarantine there
are still a lot of people who think that
the risk of quarantine is worse than the
risk of not and that the viral risk
itself is overblown and that's one of
the things that I want to address so
we'll start right there so comparing the
death rates to the flu and seeing that a
lot less people have died and then
thinking that it's overblown and it's
some kind of either state agenda to
concentrate control or mass hysteria or
something like that a number of people
that die from the flu every year
is one it's a baseline that we always
have so looking at elevation from
baseline is a critical factor because
that's changing a the way that society
functions - because it's a baseline
we've had every year we have ICU
capability for that we don't have ICU
capability for spikes above that and
that's where we start getting
catastrophic collapse of the medical
system that leads to much worse problems
3 during a flu season most people get it
very high percentage people get it
because we don't try to stop the spread
because it's not that fatal not not that
high a percentage of total people died
not that high percentage of people even
need hospitalized so we don't take very
serious measures to prevent it spread so
if a similar number of people got Kove
in nineteen as got the flu the death
numbers would be catastrophic higher
because the percentage of people that
need hospitalized and go into critical
condition and the percentage of people
that died even factoring the whole range
of what that can be is radically higher
the total number of people exposed so
far is tiny compared to the flu but it
won't stay tiny if you don't do
containment it is spreading enough that
if you don't contain it
you could get saturation you'd get
saturation in about two months meaning a
60 70 percent of the population has it
globally from where we currently are if
containment efforts didn't get put in
place containment efforts can of course
slow that curve and even stop the curve
depending upon the nature of the
containment which will make the total
number of infected people and thus
hospitalized people and deaths much much
lower also in calculating fatalities it
takes a while from the time that someone
is exposed for them to expose other
people and expose other people to get to
who the people who are going to be most
vulnerable it takes a while from the
time someone was exposed for them to
show symptoms from the time they show
symptoms to get serious enough to go to
the hospital and from the time they go
to the hospital to when they die so
there's a lot of people who are early in
that curve who are not yet being
recorded as fatalities but will
and so comparing the fatalities right
now to the flu is like a whole bunch of
statistical mistakes at once
that's just one important thing to
factor if if you got two that say 60 70
percent infection rate as you get with
the flu what just a comparison what
would the death rate be there's a few
numbers that really matter it are not in
CF are the two then most people are
focusing or not as each person that gets
it how many other people will get it
from them and CFR's case fatality rate
of the total people who are infected how
many died the other number that I think
is critically important that is not
quite as popular being tracked is of the
total number of people who get it how
many need hospitalized how many have to
go to ICU that ends up being really
critical because of the much larger
percentage that are hospitalized than
died the downstream effects of that are
very profound and they have to factor
them all three of those numbers are
variables they are not fixed just by the
nature of the virus themselves so
they're very affected by the social
response social and institutional
response so regarding the are not number
when we say the are not is two or
two-and-a-half or whatever it is this is
a statistical average first it's a guess
based on not knowing the actual number
of infected cases because we aren't
testing enough to know the actual number
of infected cases and it's an average
across people who stay at home and don't
interact with anyone and people who are
writing the subway and interacting with
everyone and are in a lot of contact and
would be what we call super spreaders so
someone might infect a thousand people
and someone else might infect no people
right so averages are very misleading
because someone can say okay two and a
half people for me but particularly
young healthy people who don't think
they're at risk of dying and so they're
like I can take a risk of getting this
more than I can fake the risk of missing
making money or whatever
is might continue to and especially if
they stay because of being relatively
healthy low symptom for a very long
period of time while being infectious
they could be super spreaders to a lot
of people so it's important oh the other
thing with regard to or not that we have
to understand is it's so obviously
that's averaged and some people will
spread much more than others but also
this topic of portal pathways being able
to spread it to a critically sensitive
community or spread it to other people
who will become super spreaders or who
would have otherwise been unaffected so
it's not it's not just like how many
people did you spread it to but did you
spread it somewhere that actually is a
really big deal getting there versus not
getting there so for instance vulnerable
populations like senior living
facilities the death rate is also
averaged across populations who mostly
all won't die versus that have very high
mortality rates so the mortality rate
and a senior care facility of people who
are both older and have comorbidities is
extremely high and so let's say one of
the workers who's going in there whether
it is a nurse or a janitor or whatever
is infected they don't know that they're
infected because there's not enough
testing they're asymptomatic it spreads
in there the fatality can that workers
from that would be very profound
if a worker goes into a prison or into a
homeless facility or into doing social
care work in Skid Row in a major
homeless area if those areas could be
totally quarantined right now and
protected from getting in we'd be much
much better off because if they get it
it's extraordinarily hard to prevent it
from spreading and when we already don't
have enough intubation equipment and ICU
capabilities those aren't the first
places it's going to go so we have to
factor not just super spreaders but
portal pathways research patient 31 in
South Korea South Korea basically had
contained and one person who wasn't
contained was in lots of social
connection and all of the other cases
that happen they're believed to have
occurred from that one person so yeah
this is a place where we're not just
factoring ourselves we're factoring the
spread and the civic responsibility
associated with it so the infection rate
is a massive variable and we can change
it that's the first thing the number of
people or the percentage of people who
get infected who have to go to the
hospital is a massive variable and who
died it's a massive variable so we see
that the death rate the fatality rate
and none of these numbers are perfect
because this is total cases in ratio to
the death cases but we don't have total
cases right anywhere because we're not
doing enough testing anywhere and the
countries aren't doing similar types and
amounts of testing so the statistics are
getting misleading but it looks like the
best numbers or say in South Korea and
the worst numbers or say in Iran or
Italy in terms of fatality so South
Korea's got like a point five percent
fatality of the total number of people
to get it less than half a percent or
around a half a percent maybe up to
about a percent die whereas you might
have like five six seven percent
depending upon how we factor the
statistics dying in some other places
partly this is going to have to do with
the susceptibility of the communities
that are getting hit obviously Seattle
had a very high case fatality rate
because it had senior from a senior home
to begin with right so that's going to
start high but it's also very much the
result of the response so if you do
early Diagnostics not only can you do
smart containment and prevent the spread
you can start early treatment and early
treatment means that the chance of
severe infection is going to go down
radically so this is a novel virus
meaning it's not a previous human virus
and so we don't have innate immunity to
it and we don't already have developed
either vaccines or drug treat
but we're obviously the whole world is
mobilizing on its learning curve as fast
as possible so it was found out that
chloroquine seems effective
hydroxychloroquine seems more effective
with less side effects the
hydroxychloroquine is a thorough myosin
combo is looking quite effective but
it's not inconsequential there's
retinopathy effects there's heart
effects so there's also limited supply
of hydroxychloroquine there's already
people who depend upon that med to live
who have lupus who are having a hard
time getting in which then starts to
cause death from other reasons right or
um not just death but hospitalization
and health issues and whatever there's
research being done on lots of
antivirals that are looking promising
and on cytokine inhibitors and on ACE -
modulators on plasma antibody transfers
so I don't think the world has ever had
a situation where we medically learned
as fast as is happening now this is
another reason to want to slow the curve
radically because we are much less well
prepared today than we will be each day
that passes for dealing with us as we're
learning more but already a lot of
doctors are treating with
hydroxychloroquine and as a thorough
myosin and other things like that and
even just getting on fluids and but
let's say that you get a treat with
those drugs early on most of those
people won't have to go to the ICU even
the same people that would have had to
go to the ICU otherwise and many of the
people that will have to go to the
hospital won't need intubated and won't
die and so early diagnostics and early
treatment also change the curve of the
illness for people who do get infected
also early diagnostics changes the curve
of how many other people they in fact
right so you can have a situation where
a very high percentage of the total
population who gets infected will end up
having to go to the ICU right like 20%
of the population you could have a
situation where almost nobody has to go
to the ICU because we're testing of
aquit ously and getting good treatments
to people so it's important to
understand how variable that is and the
same with death rates
it is not true that this is only a
serious illness for old people with
comorbidities it is mostly only fatal
for people who are older or have
comorbidities so far but half of the
people in Italy who are on intubation
which means a tube in your lungs keeping
you alive are under 60 half of them are
and if they didn't have access to that
equipment then they wouldn't stay alive
many of them and so it's important to
understand that part of why the fatality
rates are lower is because they're
depending upon life support systems that
if those life support systems went out
the fatality would go way up
now Italy's already gone to this
situation where they don't have enough
respirators and ICU capability for
everyone so there triaging and so some
people are just being led to die because
they don't have any other options so
then the death percentage goes way up
right that's the single biggest thing
that affects the percentage of people
that die is the overwhelm of ICU
capabilities and then people can't get
treated for coronavirus and so they die
also you can have a situation where the
hospital is overwhelmed so people can't
get treated for the normal stuff where
we save people's lives from heart
attacks and strokes and ambulances are
taking a long time to get to places and
bleeding looms and all those other
things so it's important to understand
that all of those numbers regarding the
spread of the infection the number of
people to get hospitalized the number of
people that die are all variable we can
change all of them and the
recommendations we're going to share or
how to make those numbers lower but
those numbers can all go radically high
if we don't respond appropriately we
could have a spread all the way to
saturation we could overwhelm the ICU
Ziff where we will if that happens the
death rate goes very high that's not to
mention yet what the follow-on effects
on the infrastructure and national
security and the economy and other
things will be but just even factoring
that so now should we get into secondary
effects sure yep so this much has not
been clear to everyone it's still not
clear to everyone but it's starting to
get clearer
and you had someone on the other day
who's written some really brilliant
articles on these things PO a said his
name Thomas boy oh yes oh yeah yeah read
his articles they're very good and you
know that kind of information is
starting to get clearer the next step we
have to look at is let's say that we
look at the health effects on people as
first order effects these are the virus
direct action first actually before I
get to second-order effects let's
address some of the unknowns here we'll
immunity be conferred don't know and so
as far as herd immunity type questions
we do not know enough to be able to make
those assessments yet because and so
again this is as of March 21st a few
days from now we might know more there
are cases injured in China and Japan of
people who were diagnosed with kovat 19
who got better and then who got it again
did they for sure get all the way better
and then got reinfected exhaustion ously
or did they not get rid of the virus all
the way and then it recirculated in
their system or was the secondary
exposure some other thing like a normal
flu or whatever we don't know yet it's
not clear enough also there are antibody
responses for the people who are getting
sick and then getting better but what is
that antibody response actually going to
do what is it priming we also just don't
know yet so it's could it is the
antibody response such that next time
someone is exposed to the virus even in
high viral load they'll get no symptoms
at all their body will fight it off so
quickly they get no symptoms maybe
they'll be awesome do they get symptoms
but less severely because their body
fights it quicker or do they actually
get a worse case because people actually
die from the immune response right they
die from a cytokine storm from the
inflammatory response that happens it
ends up overwhelming the lungs and other
other organs so interleukin 6 primarily
in TNF alpha there's drugs that are
working to block those but could
that the antibody response Prime's a
cytokine storm that's been speculated
just don't know yet because we don't
have a lot of people who've gotten
better and we know they got better we've
tested that there's zero viral load and
then they reexpose then let's say that
someone does have immunity will everyone
have the same immunity or will it be
that people who have more compromised
immune systems or primed for cytokine
storm and other people are primed to
actually have good responses there's
probably going to be a Gaussian
distribution of the type of response
that occurs or there could very well be
right the next question is how long will
the immunity last will it last for a
couple years which would be really
helpful as it didn't SARS or is the
mutation such that the antibodies last
only for a couple months in which case
this thing keeps circulating we don't
know again we don't have that kind of
long-term data the other thing is that
the virus is mutating and how wide of a
mutation will the antibodies protect
against even if they are protective is a
question right so as we know with the
Spanish flu situation it wasn't the
first round that killed the most people
it was the second round
so let's even say we got hurt immunity
we know that we don't get hurt immunity
against the flu permanently it every
year kills a bunch more people right and
we know that even if we vaccinate
against that the vaccine is not good
against the mutation so we have a
similar situation here let's say that we
didn't control this adequately and it's
with us every year like the flu now but
on top of the flu but with a much higher
fatality and it reaches saturation
numbers then we could look at this being
a meaningfully population decreasing
phenomena so let's say you get to
saturation 70% of the people are
infected and 2% of them die or because
70% are infected and it overwhelms the
IC use 5% of the people die calculate
those on country-by-country basis or
global basis those are tremendously huge
numbers right so that's a there are
numbers like 1 million there's numbers
like 10 million in the US based on
exactly how
what the death rates are and how those
curves happen but there I think the
number of soldiers that died in Vietnam
over 11 years was 50,000 or something
like that so you can look at the
multiples we're looking at so we don't
yet know about whether immunity will be
adequately conferred we don't yet know
about the rate and the severity of the
mutations and if the following mutations
will be more or less lethal we don't yet
know what the long-term health effects
of contracting this are so we know that
viruses don't just go away permanently
in many cases they go into chronic
phases so someone gets her Peas and they
can continue to get herpes right they
get HPV warts and they can continue to
get words and they can continue to
become infectious when that happens we
know that with other infections you get
chickenpox you don't get again for a
long time but then you get shingles and
then for some things like say mono then
you still have low-grade epstein-barr
that can increase likelihoods for
cancers and chronic fatigue syndrome and
things like that so what are is is there
going to be a chronic health implication
of this in addition to the existing
chronic viruses that are already part of
the health care system this is again
also a totally not known topic and then
the people who get a serious illness but
don't die the CT scans of their lungs
show very serious damage to their lungs
some of them are showing damage to the
heart cardiomyopathy and other body
systems so might there be lasting damage
it affects the duration of that person's
life even for people who and I mean not
via the viral or immunological process
but the tissue damage processes well we
know that tissue damage is occurring of
the type that normally is lasting
obviously what that looks like two or
three years later we don't yet know but
that should all tell people that this is
not something to take lightly
and that there's a good bit of unknown
also just look at a video of someone on
intubation and who's got to be intubated
for weeks like that's such an
undesirable thing to experience even if
it doesn't kill you and again back that
half of the people in Italy on
intubation are under 60 so that's a
little bit more just on the medical
effects right okay so let's say that
that is all looking at kind of just the
direct virus acting on human physiology
so now we look at second-order effects
and we say okay so what is the effect on
the medical system from spikes well
beyond the capacity of what I see use
our setup for so it's expensive to run
hospitals it's expensive to run
intensive care units and to train lots
of doctors and whatever to just be
sitting around waiting for surges so
hospitals and I see use run pretty close
to full capacity for financial
efficiency which means that really big
surges are things that are not well
prepared for some things can be
upregulated fairly quickly some things
can't like it's not very easy to build a
lot more respirators in a hurry or to
train a lot more doctors in a hurry so
if the number of people who are going to
I see use is within the capacity that
the ICU can scale up to the death
percentages will stay relatively low if
it exceeds it and the I see us to start
triaging who gets treated and who
doesn't the number of deaths the
percentage of deaths is going to go way
up so let's say that the number of
people that are going in is 2x what the
ICU czar prepared for and they can get
people in the hallways and whatever okay
that's one thing but what if it's 10x or
more this is where you start seeing what
you're seeing in Italy and you know and
worse where it's just people just can't
be treated now besides the fact that
most of the hospitals in the US are
already running low on personal
protective equipment or don't even have
it and doctors are putting themselves
and nurses putting themselves a huge
personal risk
rate of doctors and nurses getting sick
is estimated at something like two to
five x with the rate of everybody else's
and they're the people who most
critically can't get sick and there's
not enough ICU beds there's not enough
intubation equipment there's not enough
of the tests of the hydroxychloroquine
of whatever right very since doctor
friend of mine in LA told me something
like currently there's a hundred and
fifty beds and ICU left in LA there's 10
million people in LA and let's just look
at what any percentage of saturation
looks like and what any reasonable
percentage of that having to go to ICU
is and it's like oh that that can look
terrible in a hurry ring so what happens
if our doctors and nurses are getting
sick and we saw a couple thousand health
care workers and China gets that grade
and China did a good job of containing
it to one area which we haven't we now
have cases in all 50 states they were
able to mostly quarantine Hubei Province
and Wuhan and have the spread outside
much less but because of their drastic
rapid intense response and also even if
the doctors and nurses don't get sick
just wearing them out because they're
trying to save lives running so many
shifts go look at the videos of people
in ICU in Seattle in Italy and just kind
of get a sense of what that looks like
and read some of the letters that
doctors in Italy are writing that are
kind of sharing their experience so you
start to have a collapse of the health
care system and now this has all kinds
of cascading consequences for death from
all other kinds of things and chronic
health implications and whatever alright
next so let's say we try to institute a
quarantine and people don't want to
participate and so we have to have the
National Guard and the police we're
allowed to try to initiate it if you
look at the videos from South Korea and
China
and Hong Kong you'll see that the police
and the National Guard equivalents are
all wearing hazmat gear and the doctors
and the nurses and the people doing the
sanitizing and picking up the trash are
all in pretty intensive degrees of
personal protective equipment and the
very frontline high exposure ones are in
hazmat gear to the best of my knowledge
and pretty active communication about
this neither the u.s. nor the UK have
that much gear nor do they have the
training to be able to get that to the
frontline people that would need to have
it so obviously we have to find where
the surplus is get it to the most
critical people in triage get the
training up and produce more kind of
instantly because one of the things
you'll notice about many of those jobs
is that they have very high contact with
each other right police are riding in a
truck together they're in a locker room
together
National Guard etc first responders and
because of the long asymptomatic period
2 to 21 days asymptomatic and some cases
actually recover while being quite low
symptoms so you can be spreading that
entire time and we don't have you know
testing out so what happens if a
significant percentage of the police
start to get sick or the National Guard
or military or prison guards or the
people who run the utilities the
critical utilities or the supply chains
you can start to get now here's the
cascading kind of third order failures
and these are much much worse risks than
the virus right so obviously everyone
can't go on quarantine because for most
people to be able to stay home the
electricity has to stay on and the water
has to stay on the internet has to stay
on they have to have some way that
either the supermarket's have some
triage version of staying open or
delivery mechanisms happen the
pharmacies so there's a number of people
whose jobs are required to basically
mediate societal function and not having
societal collapse all of those people
need to get personal protective
equipment and/or hazmat gear based on
the degree of exposure they have and
they need
to get training for how to use it and
they need to have in Sherman of payments
so they don't go on strike this is not
the time we need or trash the people
that do trash sanitization engineers
getting sick or going on strike right
we're then you start to get additional
health plague type issues associated
trash piling up or any critical
utilities or whatever starting to have
problems but that could happen right and
we already see we saw in Italy certain
prisons being overtaken by the prisoners
because of this situation either because
the prison guards didn't want to go to
work or about sick or various things
like that now the US has a much higher
percentage of its total population in
prison than any other country the
prisons are going to be highly
vulnerable to the spread if it happens
inside of there and they know they won't
be the first people to get intubated so
what does that mean for the mindset of
you know people in there these are just
these are serious follow-on effects that
really have to be thought about and in
addressed anticipatorily now we also
have confounding effects which are
independent variables but that also
affect the overall situation the floods
are starting in the US and that's a
normal thing we get floods in the rainy
season but how do the droplets of this
disease spread and water scenarios where
everybody's walking around in ankle-deep
or knee-deep water
how do you do containment and quarantine
when you're having to move people
because of floods how does that affect
the redirection of medical and first
responders you know those types of
things right we also had a little
earthquake in Utah that was just a wake
up of like Oh the rest of the normal
disasters don't go on and hold so you
know as we come in the summer and we
think about what California's wildfire
season was like last year and think
about okay so what happens where you got
a quarantine then the wildfire start or
Florida hurricane season or whatever
right so we also have to think about the
rest of general preparedness
in those issues and where we started to
get quarantined down and now we lose
quarantine because of some other issue
and or can't respond so we get worse
death tolls or infrastructure collapse
because our responders are already
purposed somewhere else for sick or
taxed or something like that right now
we start to look at the political
effects could we have a situation where
the countries on quarantine during the
elections for the US yeah do we have
digital voting that is secure and ready
to go where people can vote from at home
no not currently and what it would take
to get there
we have no precedent for we also have no
precedent for a plague you know a
pandemic during voting if we get if to
ensure that people go and vote do we
increase the pandemic spread and have a
spike during that time and then you know
have a whole additional spike to deal
with does this change the demographics
of who's available to go significantly
so there's a whole big serious set of
questions there obviously the economic
situation we've seen trillions of
dollars of loss since this is started in
the stock market and if you take for the
US or the UK or any country or the world
you take the GDP per month and you say
okay under quarantine people are staying
home we're not just looking at a
effective asset classes because of
trading and fear and whatever and we're
not just looking at the effect of on
Airlines and a few industries but all of
the restaurants and all of the you know
sporting and cruises and in-person type
things small businesses everything under
quarantine so we're looking at not just
a effect on the financial sector but on
the actual real economics of
productivity itself and supply and
demand type dynamics themselves so then
we get what a decrease of by 30 percent
under quarantine or forty percent or
whatever of
world GDP capacity so look at what the
GDP of the US for instance per Montes
look at losing 30 or 40 percent of that
per month and the idea that that's what
has to be subsidized just for break-even
type effects not mentioning the up
ramping I see use capabilities and
diagnostic capabilities and things like
that or international aid which brings
us to the next topic there's a lot more
in economics by the way seventy percent
of Americans live paycheck to paycheck
and can't afford to be quarantined for a
while so they will push to want to keep
working and you know spread infection
for them to be able to stay home is
gonna require economic support in
stimulus packages which are already in
discussion which is really good which
should be suspension of rent and
mortgage payments and either a ubi or
some kind of food and medicine
provisioning type capabilities there's
going to need to be protection for small
businesses so there doesn't have to be
massive laying off of people because if
you have bankruptcy and collapse of
small businesses they can't rebuild
themselves that quickly there's a
learning group to be able to rebuild
things so it's like you know when you're
clear cut a forest you don't get a new
forest back right away and so there's a
lot in the economic space that has to be
addressed the geopolitical space is
actually where my biggest concerns are
so I'll share a scenario it's not the
only scenario so we see already Saudi
Arabia doing and Russia in this you know
oil price gouging kind of scenario and
that could play out all kinds of weird
ways so there's lots of different
scenarios that could occur but let's
specifically focus on us-china relations
and overall geopolitical placement first
let's look at what the epidemiology for
the whole world could be because we
don't know originally there was a hope
that this would follow seasonality and
either led up a bunch in the summer and
or as a result of temperature effects
not really hit one countries as much we
now see it spreading rapidly in Brazil
and in other
warmer Asian places and so that hope has
been kind of thwarted it looks like
there are aren't any places that are
unsusceptible so there are places that
are earlier in the curve and later in
the curve in some place that haven't
been reached yet but unless some kind of
massive measures are taken to not be
reached and they will so specifically
what happens when India gets hit China
has a huge population but they didn't
have to quarantine their whole
population they had to do some measures
across the whole population but they
were able to contain to a province
pretty strongly
what is India do with very high total
population very high population density
very high interaction low ICU per capita
capabilities low relative hygiene
capabilities for lots of population and
just imagine like okay if we don't
protect against transmission there what
happens same with Mexico City right same
with Lagos same with a number of places
Bangladesh that have high populations
multiplied by population density without
good preparedness capacities okay so now
we see and we see that first world
countries are getting destroyed right we
see that Italy is in that position and
and that other European countries right
Merkel said probably 70 percent of the
country is going to get infected
eventually like the very serious kinds
of things we see what's happening to the
EU as a result of this since they use
not actually supporting Italy and not
able to support Eastern European
countries and then China stepping in to
offer help so now China was on the front
of this curve which also and they took
very strong responses so they are the
farthest ahead of being able to offer
international aid in response China was
already the place that did most of the
manufacturing of medical equipment in
the first place and so in one way of
looking at it and China got a massive
economic hit and there were lots of
companies that wanted to pull
manufacturing out of China which could
be a massive very long term head for
China since exporters such a huge part
of their business
it affected overall you know public
sentiment towards them so in some ways
they got hit hard but on other ways you
know it's just two months later and
they're starting to loosen quarantine no
new cases in Wuhan and they're opening
Apple stores and Starbucks stores
throughout the country again right plus
offering masks and ventilators and
training and aid and you know medical
knowledge and equipment to places that
need it so we've seen that in Italy
we've seen in some Eastern European
places we saw to the EU as a whole so in
some ways China's in a stronger position
than it's ever been because they're on
the other side of this they mobilized
into a crisis wartime response type mode
and they have the Medical Response
equipment and those types of things they
were already geopolitically very savvy
with the Belden Road initiative and all
of the work they were doing to be able
to get international support and
coordination for their geopolitical
agendas the u.s. appears to be moving
into one of the weakest positions it has
been in a very long time and because of
not having early strong response and we
can't just do specialized quarantines
because there are some people in all 50
states and we don't have the Diagnostics
ready could we be in a very vulnerable
position for a long time I've heard UK
and US federal governments both talked
about 18 months now after the paper that
came out from Imperial College talking
about that so what happens if China is
in a very strong position yes in a weak
position and could they start dumping US
Treasury bonds could they start with
cyberattacks whatever not just them lots
of state actors non-state actors right
do we have if the police are redirected
then where does that open up criminality
if the government's attention is damaged
or redirected where does that open up
vulnerabilities that's obviously going
to happen everywhere but there's not as
many places in the world that would have
predatory opportunism for Italy as
they'd have for the US right
or the UK but particularly look at kind
of superpower tensions here and but
there's a thing that isn't direct war
which is just China being able to do a
good job of offering international aid
in exchange for joining the Belden Road
initiative and then oh by the way
dollars are really dirty and transmitted
coronavirus let's move to digital
currency oh by the way we have a digital
currency let's roll it out and or you
can only get our aid in the digital
currency or that was already something
that was being considered and in the
works I was a turn on to this originally
by Alex Gladstein from the human rights
foundation that there's a bunch of
countries that were already too fully
dependent upon Chinese infrastructure
like being the only telecom in many
countries and obviously the kind of
predatory debt lending for fundamental
infrastructure where they could say we
will now only accept payment and all you
need payment portal but because it's a
government-sponsored digital payments
there's no anonymity to the money at all
right so there's there's no separation
between the private sector and the
public sector there's no anonymous cash
there's a perfectly monitor of all
financial surveillance apparatus that
would also become a world currency world
reserve currency if it became the
primary one used or couldn't so I want
the u.s. to ramp up its capability to
respond to this domestically and to
shore up its vulnerabilities against all
of the kinds of national security
threats and tax on whatever that can
happen during this time and ramp up its
ability to start offering international
aid I would like the UK and the US
Department and you know for everyone
else who would be in the right place due
to a partner in that and we're nowhere
close to that but we could it would
require a world war two level
mobilization full-court press on the
capability to do it we see that the
private sectors offered involvement
already we see the China's private
sector has right and so Jack Ma saying
that he'll get the personal protective
equipment and other key things needed
for the US
but we also see Facebook and Google and
Walmart and Walgreens and you know lots
of US corporations we see that Elon said
that he'd ramp up ability to make
ventilators if needed I would really
like to see capabilities of companies
like alongs
conscripted to not just ramp up
ventilators for the US knee but also to
be able to export international aid for
the geopolitical position that that
represents I also want to be very
careful that in in engaging the private
sector the companies that are most
capable of helping in the private sector
the ones that already had too much power
and we're almost monopolies so Amazon
has amazing logistics capabilities to
get everything to people's door well
they're under quarantine and they were
already basically became the market
right Facebook has an amazing ability to
do contact tracing where if anyone is
infected we can probably see everyone
who they were engaged with and be able
to help predict where the curves are
going to hit the icy use but we don't
want to turn those abilities on and then
leave them on forever so we have to be
able to engage the private sector in a
way that engages their capacities but
doesn't collapse democracy and have
regulatory capture even more as a result
of it and data capture which is where we
can neither be slow in our response here
because of the rate of doubling nor can
in our fastness we be hasty and make
dumb moves which means extremely smart
fast sense making and coordination is
absolutely needed so there's a lot more
examples that we could give we haven't
even talked about what the mental health
crisis consequences are going to be the
change and social fabric are going to be
what is the effect of the total number
of old people that die on social
grieving and family structures what is
the a whole generation of kids all
missing school at the same time like
there's a lot of things to factor here
how many marriages only stay together
because the people avoid each other most
of the time and you know I'm quarantined
and the kids stay home from school and
they have two parents who normally work
now one of the masks to stay home and
the dad's a utility worker in the
nurse and neither of them can stay home
and like this all these types of things
to consider I mean you've just outlined
a few of the effects of the of the
quarantine so some people might be
thinking well is the quarantine worse
than the than the disease itself not
even close
having if herd immunity occurs which we
don't know it needs to occur slow and up
that it doesn't overwhelm the ISEE use
which means we still have to do
everything we can to stop the spike from
ICU overwhelm if the herd immunity
doesn't occur all the more we want to
stop the ICU and stop people from
getting it because it doesn't even help
to get it and get over with it and we
need to be able to ramp up the
diagnostics and the early treatments
that are going to be able to be the
actual longer-term answer losing a bunch
of our doctors and nurses having
collapse of critical infrastructure
having so much national damage that's
occurring from the death tolls that we
become more vulnerable to attacks of
various kinds we've already seen
increase in kind of coordinated disinfo
attacks that look to be state actor and
some non-state actor attacks and cyber
attacks no think about it like frame
control right from a kind of theory of
war placed we would much rather
voluntarily quarantine and not and have
the people that are needed to run
critical stuff still be healthy and able
to run the critical stuff then they're
sick and they can't and we can't respond
if we want to and now we're on the
defense of whatever else is coming right
so to have frame control of this you
absolutely want to be able to respond
anticipatorily and 18 months of
quarantine would be really really bad
but two or three months people can live
with people like churches need to come
together and say we're not gonna come
together physically but we're going to
make sure that everyone who's lonely is
getting talked to on the phone and we're
doing Skype calls and we're doing you
know spiritual psychological support
we're making sure that the people who
don't have resources and the older
vulnerable people are getting the
resources we're being used as hubs to
you know provision the gear there's
there's lots of things that can be done
to be able to support so here's the
proposal that I recommend that I would
like to see happen I would like to see
for the US and I I don't know the UK
situation as well but I believe it's
probably quite similar I would like to
see a total nationwide quarantine
immediately effective immediately and
what that means is if you don't have a
job that societal function requires you
to go out to work for then you stay home
so if you run utilities or critical
supply chain or first responder or
whatever then you need to get then the
government has to be able to provision
personal protective equipment and hazmat
gear and training to all of those people
the training is critical because even if
you have the gear and you use it the
tiniest bit wrong touch the outside of
something while you're removing it then
it's completely worthless and this is
again a situation where the money that
was cut to the CDC in office of
pandemics and like that was really
disastrous because we need more of these
people to have been trained already and
have gear already and to have earlier
response capacity and better
coordination had we responded early we
would have had a recurring kong's right
you shut down the borders tend to the
first few people that are sick and
that's it right then you have a South
Korea type case where a lot of people
get infected but you so you can't just
kind of prevent anyone getting infected
but you respond very strong you do the
quarantines you do the personal
protective equipment and the sanitizing
and the social distancing and you do the
very strong Diagnostics early on and
tracing and
you have the curve flatten very steeply
and it's important understand that South
Korea is a democracy this isn't day only
totalitarian autocracies conclude
draconian measures when the draconian
measures will seem very humane and sane
compared to like tiny little Italy
Italy's the size of not China but the
Hubei Province has already had more
people die than China and it's still
early in their curve so that actually
should be seen as radically inhumane to
not respond quickly and I mean we're not
seeing these responses yet in I mean the
UK in the US for example and and
generally why do you think that is what
do you think it is that people are not
getting is it the nature of the
exponential curve or what's what do you
think of the blocks right now I think
the Imperial College piece that came out
really changed the UK and the u.s. is
perspective it seems because they they
got oh fuck this isn't the flu this is
serious and we collapse of ICU looks
really ugly and we don't even know about
convert immunity so the whole just naive
this is not going to be that big a deal
or we all need hurt immunity anyways and
we'll just call a little bit of the
population those are just gibberish
ideas and I think that we were running
on gibberish ideas there's of course
alternate hypotheses about different
intentions I don't think that it matters
to speculate on that right now I think
what matters is to just get appropriate
responses and the appropriate response
right now is that even though we have
people in all 50 states that are
infected and but that's not evenly
distributed we still have 50% of the
cases in five or six counties which
means that we do have to do a very smart
coordinated triage approach where do we
get the rate-limiting gear the
Diagnostics does have to be equal
quarantine everywhere no right what does
a smart approach look like requires much
better coordination and much faster
responses than we've had but as is right
now the total percentage of the
population affected is so small
right but with a three-day doubling time
that changes very quickly and you reach
saturation in less than two months now
when we say reach saturation like 70% of
the population list in two months that's
if no measures are instituted we can
already see they're being instituted
even if not the federal government level
California just implemented a policy
statewide and many cities are
implementing at their city level and a
lot of people are voluntarily quarantine
so we're going to dampen the curve but
it needs to be dampened much more
radically so why have we not before it's
some combination of miscalculating being
more afraid of the economic hits and not
calculating how bad the economic hits of
it hitting catastrophic infection levels
would be just rampant coordination
failure cut resources to the areas that
would normally know how to respond to
this appropriately but I don't think I
don't want anyone focused on who did
what dumb things right now which creates
more coordination failure I want
everyone working together in a
nonpartisan way to just stop this then
we can come back to domestic politics of
that kind but if we have any kind of red
blue left/right nonsense right now lots
more people will die and the
catastrophic effects will be worse so
this needs to be unified response within
countries and between countries they're
also obviously viruses don't give you
shit about borders they only care about
transmission and so that's the other
thing is that national governments
cannot respond to pandemics they can
respond but they can't solely respond
that requires international coordinated
responses I want to see nationwide
quarantine it's the only way to stop the
spread because the spread is human to
human or human to surface to human and
if you stop the social transmission it
stops it's important to understand the
that viruses don't care about speeches
or politics or economic interests like
they're just it's biologists physics and
this is one of the things that we you
know in in general there's this truism
that the generals who are at the top of
the military during peacetime are not
necessary the ones we're best at winning
wars so when we move into wartime
sometimes they start losing battles and
we kind of have to rotate through a few
times till we find people like Churchill
and patents that are good at winning
wars that we wouldn't necessarily want
these times because kind of politicians
or diplomats I see that happening now
where you can for a lot of issues that
are just are social constructs speeches
and what people think and what they feel
and being able to just dope the
information ecology is adequate because
we're just trying to move human
sentiment viruses don't give a shit
about that so we're actually dealing
with base physics again right and
overwhelmed ICU doesn't give a shit
about that and critical infrastructure
there's a lot of these things which like
oh we're actually dealing with physics
again and so doing politics will not
help them so anyone who only knows how
to do politics and is at the top because
they were selected for during that time
we'll just keep failing and whoever
knows how to actually do real physics
biology logistics capable stuff will get
up regulated during this time
okay so quarantine to stop the spread
now I would like to see that called for
it a nationwide level I'd also like to
see it called for at a statewide level
because if it isn't called of the nation
level states can do that right I would
like to see it called for by mayor's at
a city level I would like to see the
celebrities come out and I'll tell
everyone using their all the channels
they have hey stay the fuck home because
right now people pay more attention to
celebrities than to epidemiologists even
in a life-or-death situation so the
celebrity should confer their celebrity
power to the epidemiologists and save
lives they don't usually have the
opportunity to save lives and help
national security and all those things
right now the way they did before
and if they're left oriented save lives
if they're right oriented national
security again it doesn't
matter it's the same thing on both sides
at this particular point I'm not saying
that both left and right wouldn't care
about both things I just mean whatever
it is someone cares about it's gonna be
the same answer here so all of the
approaches that can be taken to stop
social transmission should be the first
order and then in order for that to
happen we have to do the economic
support and stimulus packages that the
people will actually stay home and that
can occur so that means stopping rents
and mortgages insurance that small
businesses won't go out of business and
other businesses that are larger
businesses but that are totally
dependent upon human contact won't go
out of business through tax credits
through subsidies through whatever types
of simulus packages are needed the ubi
or other kinds of food and medicine
provisioning those types of actions have
to be taken they don't all have to be
taken at once because we're gonna have
to figure them out and they're gonna
have their own consequences president
should come out and declare the key ones
and say each day will be working on
adding to this as makes sense and as we
see what the needs are but we will take
care of this and so that people actually
can stay home and that should be seen as
a patriotic duty it should be called for
as a patriotic duty also in addition to
be able to make the quarantine happen
not only do you need the economic
support all the people who can't be on
quarantine need to have the personal
protective gear hazmat gear training
that they need and so that should be an
absolute top priority and that's we
mentioned many of the areas but you know
you can factor what those areas are
healthcare first responders
infrastructure utilities etc vulnerable
populations particularly need very hard
quarantine measures so the seniors
facilities the prisons the homeless
facilities the immuno compromised places
those need very hard quarantines because
we can't have spreading and yeah we
can't
we can't have spreading happening within
those it'll be too much of a disaster so
those should be particularly fiercely
protected so next after quarantine and
all that it takes to make that happen
the focus is a full-court press with the
private sector and the government
working together to ramp a high quality
Diagnostics so that we can do a bit
witness Diagnostics so we can move from
a total quarantine to a smart quarantine
so a lot of people will protest we don't
have that many tests yet that's true or
the turnaround time on the test is too
slow or there's too many false negatives
or the tests only show up after people
have been sick it for a while yes all
that's true on the tests that we've had
so when I'm saying we need to ramp up
Diagnostics adequate Diagnostics what I
mean is it's not a single strategy we've
been collecting all of the diagnostic
technology surplus new diagnostic tech
in one place so that we can be seeing
which ones have the capability to get
what types of things where and have a
multi-pronged strategy if there's anyone
who has real capability to help that
financial or logistic please contact me
can do that through facebook Messenger
but so we need to get the tests that
currently exists even though they're
inadequate to all the places that need
them most so a triage to the places
where the most spread can occur right
there the following tracing of contacted
individuals the counties that have the
most impact etc we need to ramp the
production of tests that can be ramped
in time even if their partial tests even
though antibodies show up too late to be
able to do prevention we need antibody
tests because we want to be able to see
his immunity conferred and if so who's
immune because I'd be very helpful the
kind of testing that I care most about
at this point is testing
that can detect cases as early as
possible after exposure with very high
sensitivities a very low rate of false
negatives very fast turnaround time and
not having rate limiting reagents and
this is the drive-through style testings
health Korea implemented there are a few
companies that have technologies that
are much better that can ramp in time
and we're working on those those need
capital and support so that being said
if people have that but the drive-thru
type testing so let's just imagine a
scenario where Walmart in Walgreens type
parking lots get drive-through test
capability so that somebody pulls in
automatically video camera registers
their license plate their driver's
license gets taken they're tested if
they are positive they go directly into
quarantine as a result they get early
treatment and they don't have to go to
ICU and we're able to separate a
quarantine people being quarantined at
home means the whole family gets it in
the most vulnerable people get it so
being able to have quarantine facilities
where then the rest of the family is
treated as exposed and we get
Diagnostics to them but if they haven't
already all been infected they don't
have to be is important and yeah people
can get on early treatments and we can
separate people who need to go to ICU
for normal non coronavirus reasons
versus those with coronavirus and be
able to separate facilities for that
we're also going to see that as the
doctors and nurses get sick but if they
have access to early testing so they can
get on early treatment many of them
either because their symptoms wouldn't
have been that bad anyways because
they're young and healthy or because of
the early treatment we'll be able to
keep working but they can't run the risk
of infecting other people so you can
have the negative pressure
Kove aid facilities and infected doctors
and nurses on treatment working there
and uninfected doctors and nurses in the
other place where people are coming in
for heart attacks and strokes and other
things like that so people drive in they
go into an appropriate quarantine and
response if they're positive if they're
negative
they get to park and go into Walmart and
go shopping and the pharmacies have the
meds that people need the personal
protective gear and Lysol and hand
sanitizers provision through those kinds
of places the food is available we can
also see the Conscription obviously of
delivery services uber left or -
whatever mean Amazon capabilities in
terms of delivering stuff to people to
be able to help make the Quarantine
happen but so what I see is that we come
off of total quarantine with a smart
quarantine where those who are either
not infected have never been infected or
are infected but have no more viral
shedding so we need tests that can
determine total viral load also if up
front we can determine total viral load
we can determine how serious the case is
likely to get and what kinds of
treatments are warranted factoring the
treatments have some side effect risk
but also afterwards we want to make sure
that there's no more viral shedding so
when does someone come off quarantine
well it can't be an X number of days
because there's going to be a long
tailed distribution of how long people
are still contagious we it actually has
to be based on adequate testing and so
then people who were either not infected
or are no longer infected can go back to
work and you know off of quarantine
still with personal protective gear
social distancing wiping down doorknobs
all those types of things because they
have to assume that some people who are
infected are still out until the total
case number drops to very very low which
is exactly what China is doing and South
Korea is doing once the total case
number is very low then life can return
to normal but this can happen in like
eight to ten weeks where we go from
total quarantine to smart quarantine
without a complete overwhelm and the ICU
is going to be overwhelmed no matter
what but without a complete break of the
medical system and without a complete
break of the US or global economy now if
you start thinking about trillions of
loss and market value in the amount of
subsidy per month being in the closer to
trillions type range of meaningful
percentage of a trillion then whatever
number of billions are needed to ramp
the Diagnostics
obviously make sense right to be able to
go from a total quarantine where most
people aren't infected to a smart
quarantine where everyone infected is
quarantined and the other people aren't
obviously during that time we're also
going to be ramping the ISEE use
capabilities and we're going to be
ramping treatment so treatments from
antivirals to vaccines to ace to
modulators to cytokine modulator czar
all being developed super rapidly and
again if we have a situation where
people can get early diagnostics and
then get treated and basically be fine
and have very little symptoms and not
good ICU not be intubated that's a very
different world in a month or in two
months even in weeks we'll have much
better knowledge on treatment than we
have today we'll have more a bit quittez
availability of the treatment and the
logistics capability to triage and get
it where it's needed the Diagnostics
will be ramping so quarantine and all
the things it takes to make that happen
ramp the Diagnostics to become
completely ubiquitous high quality
Diagnostics to move into sorts mark
quarantine and the ramp of treatments if
vaccines get somewhere awesome I'm if
the antibody transfers get somewhere
awesome but I'm not counting on those
because of mutations and the main issues
but I am expecting the treatments to be
very effective and then that's all
dealing with the medical stuff then it's
also ramp all of the vulnerabilities and
national security type threats during
this time and then ramp the ability for
international aid and paying attention
to the geopolitical position that we
don't become myopic those are the
responses at a national level that I
really most want to see and as far as at
a bottom-up level we're seeing
incredible responses of community
self-organizing and private sector
getting engaged and organizing that
getting the personal protective
equipment and various things to various
places but we're also seeing a lot of
duplication of efforts
and not great coordinating so if anyone
who has the capability in the interest
to do something can look to see who's
already doing it are there groups that
have good ability and more traction and
join them that would be really more
helpful if you're wanting to see how to
make your city do a good job of planning
if whether you're a mayor or you're just
a community leader there are some cities
that have already done a really good job
copy/paste and then also share best
practices if you're doing something for
your city or your state figure out how
to share it with the other cities and
states or if for your church or the
other church complexes so that we have
the maximum amount of learning sharing
the least amount of duplication so
Daniel you've been writing about and
talking about systemic risk existential
risk for an awfully long time we put out
quite a few films on the channel around
that so you've been warning about these
topics for a long time how are you how
are you feeling now that it does seem
that we're now facing a real world
example of the sort of things that
you've been talking about warning about
for a long time well I mean it's it's
been obvious to anyone paying attention
that this was eminent I mean Bill Gates
has been talking about our
susceptibility for a pandemic for quite
some time and as high-profile as he has
didn't have us get prepared and Kovan
didn't cause Australia to burn last
month right Australia burned for other
reasons and we haven't seen a whole
continent be decimated in a natural
disaster like that in recent history and
the climate change where we had very hot
dry period and it already used up the
groundwater and whatever in Australia
that led to that happening is the same
thing that's gonna cause 50 Celsius heat
waves hitting India and Bangladesh that
destroyed crops and have vast numbers of
people in fatal circumstances just
associated with that and then does that
lead to war over the scarce resources
does that cleave long Muslim Hindu lines
does that turn into an india-pakistan
more bolson ROO end up
the Brazilian Amazon Ecuador is also
under massive threat at the headwaters
of the Amazon the hydrological pump of
the Amazon is where a huge amount of the
rainfall from North America comes from
so it's not just a South American issue
and the lack of drop in the rainfall for
North America would be a catastrophic
collapse of North America so it should
be seen as a national security threat
for North America there are so many of
these issues and so the I'm hoping that
right now
people are feeling it and recognizing
that okay Australia was actually a big
deal and this pandemic is actually a big
deal
and there's actually a the climate
change mediated events and it is a force
amplifier for other things it's a big
deal and these aren't the same issue
it's not like there's one issue but
they're all caused by the same
underlying fragile civilization of
structures so the here's the closing
frame I'd like to share that's just a
simple frame as I can there are a lot of
people that have a status quo bias or a
positivity bias that doesn't want to
look at negative things or things that
everything will be fine or things that
risks are always overblown or something
like that and they say something to the
effect of hey look we have thought the
rapture was come in since the 16th
century that the end was nigh hmm and
y2k was a bunch of hype in 2012 was a
bunch of hype and SARS and Ebola and
those things were a bunch of hype and
yes there's problems in the world but
they're less bad than they used to be
and they just drive innovation and
that's the curve I think that this
perspective is complete dangerous
nonsense and it is more of a bias
response than it is actually a
thoughtful response because
here are the factors I would like people
to think about regarding the uniqueness
of the time we're in now relative to all
other times and yet our intuition is
conditioned and even our reason is
conditioned from past experience in past
time so we have to factor that all of
the previous civilizations and previous
empires died at some point they failed
and none of them were eternal
civilizations we don't still have a
Byzantine or a Egyptian or Mayan or
Aztec or Roman or whatever Empire they
died for reasons associated with
self-induced collapse oftentimes they
actually cut down all the trees and
Easter Island did themselves or led to
infernal inviting that created descent
and collapse but oftentimes even if they
were overtaken by external enemies they
were overtaken by enemies that were
smaller than once they had protected
against previously because they had
underwent institutional decay so so far
nobody has figured out how to avoid
institutional decay especially as they
scale a long term so we only know how to
make civilizations that collapse various
timeframes democracies collapse on a 2
to 300 year timeframe the u.s. is coming
up on 250 years right now and we're
pretty near a collapse type scenario for
a number of reasons it's actually very
interesting to think about the way that
the u.s. emerged as the superpower
coming out of World War two that it
didn't enter World War two as in the way
that the European countries got
radically downregulated in their
relative dominance in the world via
World War two and how easily a situation
like this could do the same thing where
China comes out of this the way the u.s.
came out of World War two if you want a
democracy or a republic to last longer
than the amount of time they've ever
lasted you have to reboot them because
institutional decay does occur so
reboots are needed which is a super
important topic but we only know how to
make civilizations that collapse but for
the first time ever we have a fully
globalized civilization so collapse
means something it's summer meant
for we have caused environmental damage
locally that desertified the topsoil we
couldn't feed the people but we could
never actually make the entire biosphere
fucked up right we couldn't do species
extinction at scale everywhere or mess
the entire oceans up or things like that
we don't have a Chinese civilization in
a u.s. civilization because if either of
them fully failed the other one would
also fail because of completely
dependent interconnected supply chains
and completely interdependent biosphere
type dynamics so we are facing a
collapse of a civilization or an empire
but where the scale of it is
unprecedented the next part that is
really critical to get is that we have
used our power either directly
militarily in ways that cause harm or
indirectly through in ways that cause
harm through social stratification
pollution and renewable resource
externalities of various kinds but we
never had tech where even if we wanted
to we could fuck up everything at a
global scale until world war ii that was
the beginning of us having truly
globally catastrophic technology and the
Romans couldn't fuck everything up if
they want to do at a global scale with
the technology they had so that's why
the development of the bomb in World War
two created the emergence of a world
system that was completely focused on
not using our new technology and in the
long arc of human history world war two
was like a second ago and that was the
beginning of us having truly globally
catastrophic capability so if you're
using any forecasting from before that
it's nonsense in terms of what kind of
harm we didn't do because we also
couldn't do okay
the only stuff that's relevant is what
kind of harm could we do and we did
right so then factor the new capability
so World War two the Bretton Woods world
we made the United Nations and we made
the World Bank and we made the entire
set of Bretton Woods agreements and all
the whole world structure to make sure
that we didn't use our new technology
and that the super
ours didn't fight but to the history of
the world major empires had always
fought so we needed to do something that
we had never done and we were able to do
that because of a few things we were
able to create debt based finance to be
able to grow the economy rapidly so
there was so much abundance we didn't
have to have scarcity based Wars but of
course that based finance is
unsustainable you can't do it forever
because you can't run an exponential
curve on a finite planet where there's
actually materials economy that's
involved forever right and so but we
could do it for some time also at the
time of the bread and Bretton Woods
solutions we weren't near planetary
boundaries anywhere we didn't have
climate change we didn't have dead zones
and oceans we didn't have biodiversity
loss we didn't have peak phosphorus or
Amazon threat or any of those things
right and one catastrophic weapon that's
very hard to make it's very hard to
enrich uranium there's only a few places
that even have uranium mines two
superpowers that have it that can both
spy on each other pretty perfectly
mutually assured destruction is possible
but today we have dozens of catastrophic
weapons not one catastrophic weapon we
have many dozens of actors that have
them including non-state actors and many
of the technologies aren't hard to
produce we have much more systemic
fragility it's important to understand
that when you make something very
efficient you also make it fragile right
if you're operating your ICU very
efficiently it can't handle spikes if
you're operating your infrastructure
efficiently I can't handle spikes if you
have a supply chain that's very
efficient and you get collapse anywhere
you can get cascading collapse if you
have lots of interacting dynamics where
a drought somewhere leads to people
having to move to already for resource
scarce areas that leads to war an
escalating war on already existing
political tensions where larger weapons
happen those types of cascade and
amplifier scenarios are also unique to
this time in terms of their their scale
their connectedness and so we have an
explosion of risk happening at this time
and
also in terms of exponential technology
curves as we can see with coronavirus
we're not good at having an intuition
for exponential curves our intuition has
never really interacted with exponential
curves very much so we're not
conditioned to even notice what they are
we're used to things that have very have
more normal growth curves than that so
our intuition for time scales is quite
bad so the underlying biosphere the
underlying infrastructure the underlying
social tensions are getting more fragile
there's more interconnectivity for
cascade failures and our overall impact
capability is increasing exponentially
and as we can see our intelligent
coordinated responses are shitty this is
the underlying situation we could have
completely prevented this virus
fortunately the death percentage on this
one is not that bad so if we don't get
our shit together this will be terrible
but we can get our shit together for
this and deal with it and use it to
harden our capability to deal with
catastrophic risks of all kinds and
actually get much smarter about this
issue because so as we're ramping our
diagnostic capabilities and our response
capabilities for this we also want to be
for the next round of mutation that
could occur and not just the next round
of mutation for this chrome virus but
also whatever else comes next we can see
avian flu 's happening in factory farms
around the world like you know
so we want to be upregulated to
pandemics but we also want to be
upregulated to all of the catastrophic
risks this one we were not prepared for
and now we're having to deal with it in
real time but had it been a Carrington
event taking out the electrical grid it
would be so much more catastrophic and
so we can prepare for it but we can't
deal with it once it's happens that's
one of the key things there's a lot of
issues that once they've happened the
it's just really terrible but preparing
for it is doable and so one of the
lessons hopefully is there's a lot of
shit that you just have to
be prepared for ahead of time as opposed
to deal with once it's occurred this one
is hopefully something that up regulates
our response there and has us pay
attention to systemic fragility and
explosion of catastrophic risk and the
inadequacy and atrophy of our overall
governance systems and that neither the
government mechanisms nor the market
mechanisms adequately dealt with this so
we need much better collective
intelligence systems to be able to deal
with risks and the current ones we have
so as we are up regulating a response to
this both the immediate and the second
third fourth order effects we want to
also be create not making things worse
like creating total monopolies by the
way we wrongly engage the private sector
or whatever and we want to make sure
that we're setting up capacity to handle
the next ones better
Daniel thank you very much for making
time likewise thank you David as the
tech revolution continues to destroy old
media the Internet is fueling a new
intellectual awakening television made
people look stupider than they were it
turns out that people are smarter with
longer attention spans then we thought
I'm a journalist and filmmaker for many
years I made documentaries for the likes
of the BBC and channel 4 but I don't
think the mainstream media can provide
the level of analysis and insight we
need for the extraordinary times we're
going through where the old structures
that made sense of the world break down
it's like we're entering just entering
into the underworld and it's a descent
we're feeling everything starting to
shake and the center cannot hold
and when our ways of thinking break down
it's the rebels and the Renegades who
dare to think differently who are needed
to reboot the system and so what's
happening is that people are perceiving
because it's becoming increasingly
obvious that all of these artifacts of
the way that we've gone about doing
civilisation are breaking down and
failing in a way that is no longer easy
to pretend isn't happening and so as a
consequence this triggers a deep
visceral sense and
good thing right because that deep
visceral sense is the return to the
elimin or the return to the mystery the
shift that we are on the precipice of is
not like the shift from the Dark Ages to
the enlightenment it's like more like a
shift from single cell to multicellular
life these are the people and ideas
rebel wisdom is searching out to try to
make sense of the growing chaos the
evolution screwed up it handed us the
tools to recognize that we don't have to
value the game that it is playing and
that we can now repurpose the hardware
to something that's actually worthwhile
that's what I actually had to open is
that if enough people can come to that
realization then then we wake up and not
in some bullshit evangelical megachurch
kind of way of being born again but in
in a truly initiatory way being going
again of like I know my purpose I know
my part and I'm willing to practice
resurrection I'm willing to offer my
life fully and freely in love in every
moment and then we're invincible like
then we can turn things on a dime it's
also about trying to create a new form
of conversation one based on genuine
dialogue letting go of ideology and
fixed ideas so we want to be a place
that hosts this new form of conversation
both online and at our events check out
our films join the conversation and to
get early access to some great films and
exclusive content please consider
supporting us on patreon
you